Guide to the Army Research Office--Durham (AROD) records, 1957-1982
Duke University. University Archives
Army Research Office--Durham (AROD) records 1957-1982
Duke University. University Archives
United States. Army Research Office--Durham.
2.7 linear feet Extent: approx. 200 items
The Office of Ordnance Research (OOR), U.S. Army, a Class II military institution, established offices on the Duke University campus in June 1951. On January 16, 1961 the OOR ceased to exist and was instead re-designated as the Army Research Office-Durham (AROD) under the command of the Chief, Research and Development. The 1960s and 1970s saw a weakening in the working relationship between the military and the scientific communities. In the spring of 1975, ARO left the Duke campus and moved to the Research Triangle Park, ten miles southeast of Durham. Collection contains materials pertaining to the mission and organization of the U.S. Army Office of Ordinance Research, the forerunner of the Army Research Office-Durham (AROD). The materials in the collection span the years 1957-1982.
uaarod
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Army Research Office--Durham (AROD) records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1970, 1977, 1984.
Historical Note
The Office of Ordnance Research (OOR), U.S. Army, a Class II military institution, established offices on the Duke University campus in June 1951. Marcus E. Hobbs, Chairman of the Department of Chemistry, served as acting chief scientist until Tomas J. Killian took over in a permanent capacity. Hobbs was instrumental in developing the "skeleton of the organization" which continued throughout the life of the organization with only minor adjustments. The organization was divided into four main divisions chemistry, mathematics, engineering, and physics. Scientists to fill the top slots were drawn primarily from Duke University, with others from the University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill, North Carolina State, and Virginia Polytech.
OOR first occupied the Hanes Mansion, but after 6 years, the burgeoning Office had outgrown the available space. In December 1958, OOR moved into a new building that was built for them on the Duke campus north of the School of Engineering. The OOR entered a lease arrangement with the University for the space helping to cover the cost of construction.
On January 16, 1961 the OOR ceased to exist and was instead re-designated as the Army Research Office-Durham (AROD) under the command of the Chief, Research and Development.
The 1960s and 1970s saw a weakening in the working relationship between the military and the scientific communities. In the spring of 1975 ARO left the Duke campus and moved to the Research Triangle Park ten miles southeast of Durham.
Collection Overview
Collection contains materials pertaining to the mission and organization of the U.S. Army Office of Ordinance Research, the forerunner of the Army Research Office-Durham (AROD). Materials include summaries of the activities of the Duke/AROD coordination office for the fiscal years 1966, 1969-1971, and a scrapbook dated 1959. The scrapbook contains photographs of Duke officials, Ordnance office chiefs, various dedication events and ceremonies, event guest lists, official luncheons, and RTP exhibit, all from 1959. The materials in the collection span the years 1957-1982.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Hobbs, Marcus E., 1909-; Gross, Paul Magnus, 1895-1986; United States. Army Research Office; United States. Office of Ordnance Research -- History; White, Peregrine
Related Material
Marcus E. Hobbs Papers, 1935-1980
Duke University Archives
A. Kenneth Pye, Chancellor, Records and Papers, 1960-1983
Duke University Archives
Lucius A. Bigelow Papers, 1915-1973
Duke University Archives
Photograph Collection, 1861-2006
Duke University Archives
Douglas M. Knight Records, 1949-1970
Duke University Archives
Vice President for Business and Finance Records, 1962-1985
Duke University Archives
Terry Sanford Records and Papers, 1945-1998
Duke University Archives
A. Hollis Edens Records, 1949-1960
Duke University Archives
J. Deryl Hart Records, 1957-1980 (bulk 1960-1963)
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Army Research Office - Durham, 1963-1982 (Box 1)
  - "A Summary of Activities and Expenditures of the Duke/ARO-D Coordination Office During Fiscal Year 1966 (Box 1)
  - "A Summary of Activities and Expenditures of the Duke/ARO-D Coordination Office During Fiscal Year 1969 (Box 1)
  - "A Summary of Activities and Expenditures of the Duke/ARO-D Coordination Office During Fiscal Year 1970 (Box 1)
  - "A Summary of Activities and Expenditures of the Duke/ARO-D Coordination Office During Fiscal Year 1971 (Box 1)
  - Office of Ordinance Research: Synopsis of Philosophy and Operations, 1957 Jan. (Box 2)
  - Proceedings of the Sixth Conference ofthe Design of Experiments in Army Research Development and Testing, 1961 Dec. (Box 2)
  - A Historical Summary, 1961 Jan. 1-June 30 (Box 2)
  - A Historical Summary, 1961 July 1-Dec. 31 (Box 2)
  - A Historical Summary, 1962 Jan. 1-June 30 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1959 (Box 3)